Good day everyone, in this video we'll be
demonstrating our game project Rockfall a 3D space shooter.
Here we will be discussing about the architecture
and main components, coding highlights, assets and folder
structure, build and run instructions and known issues
and possible improvements.
But before that let us demonstrate the game
first.
So we'll be running the game and we
press this button, so
that's basically the game.
To start let's look at the high-level
architecture of this project.
The core logic is handled by the Game
Manager, a singleton that controls the overall game
state, switching between the main menu and the
game over screens as well as managing object
spawning.
Handling player control is in the Input Manager.
The script translates the inputs from the on
-screen virtual joystick and fire button so the
ship can use them.
It's in here.
The player ship.
The player ship itself is an structured invisible
container object.
It holds the logic scripts like steering and
thrust while the child object handles the actual
3d model.
This keeps the logic separate from the visuals.
So the ship is in here.
So if we put this in here we
can see our ship.
So let's remove this.
And next our main objective is to defend
the space station.
So here is our space station.
A static target that uses a damage taking
script to track itself.
The enemies are asteroid prefabs which are rigid
bodies designed to deal damage on impact.
Generated by an asteroid spawner that aims them
toward the station.
And finally to manage visibility we have the
indicator manager.
This system calculates the position of off-screen
objects like the station or enemies and places
2d markers on the ui so the player
knows which direction it will look.
Now let's dive into the code implementation with
ship movement.
In shipcrust.cs, so I'll put it in
here.
So let's open this first.
So in shipcrust.cs, we have we achieve
constant forward motion using transform translate multiplying vector
forward by speed and delta time.
For turning, shipsteering.cs takes the delta data
from the input manager.
So in the game we have our ship
steering in here.
We use quaternion.slurp here to create the
rotation and specifically to dampen the z-axis
ensuring the ship levels out and doesn't roll
uncontrollably.
Next is the weapon system.
So within here let's open this first.
So the ship weapon script handles the shooting
via fire method.
Where is the fire method?
We have it in here.
That alternates between predefined fire points on the
wings.
This is triggered by coroutine in the input
manager called fire weapons which continuously calls the
fire method as long as the button is
held down.
For the damage logic, we use two scripts.
So damage and collide detects the hit using
standard unity physics triggers.
So we have it in here.
It then calls the take damage and the
victim's damage taking component which deducts health and
destroys the object instantiating an explosion prefab if
health is hit zero.
One of the more interesting feature is the
off-screen indicators.
In the indicator.cs wherein we have it
in here.
In the indicator.cs script we use camera
world to viewport point to point the 3d
position of a target into 2d screen space.
We then check if the target is behind
the camera and use matf.clamp to pin
the arrow to the edge of the screen.
And finally for the environment, the asteroid spawner
uses random.unit on unit sphere to pick
a spawn point and look what to aim
the asteroid.
Meanwhile the game manager runs a check in
the update loop.
If the player exceeds the predefined boundary radius,
it triggers a warning or a game over.
So we have it in here.
The game over UI and the boundary.
Moving on to the project structure.
We have organized the assets for clarity.
So we have the assets in here.
The models folder which is in here contains
all our 3d assets like the ship and
station files which are set to generate colliders
and import.
The objects folder is where we keep our
prefabs.
So we have it in here.
The fully configured ship, shots and explosion ready
for instantiation.
And next our scripts folder is organized by
function separating core systems like the game manager
from component logic like ship steering.
So early on we already showed it wherein
we have it in here.
Finally the UI folder wherein we have it
in here wherein we store our sprites for
the joystick and fonts while the skybox holds
the texture assets used to create the deep
space background.
And next would be to test the game
properly especially the mobile inputs with the unity
remote app.
This allows us to connect a mobile device
and use actual touch screen to drive the
virtual joystick inside the editor.
When ready to export we go to the
build settings or the build profiles.
Select the target platform like android and click
switch platform wherein it will be in here
if for example you're in here.
So we click that and press the build.
So now let's go to the known issues
and possible improvements for this project.
So to wrap up there are a few
missing features in the current build.
Gameplay wise the ship doesn't have a damage
component yet which means the player is invincible
and can't actually be destroyed.
To fix this logic, logic could be added
to handle ship destruction and show a health
bar.
So I think we've already fixed this issue
wherein after a while if the station gets
too many or achieves or it's been hit
many times enough to drain itself it will
be destroyed and the game over menu will
be shown.
But since it takes too long we won't
show it in here.
And next also the asteroid spawning stays the
same the whole time.
It doesn't get harder the longer you play.
A way to improve this would be to
simply increase the spawn rate or speed as
the game goes on.
Visually the game looks a bit plain right
now.
Potential improvements include swapping the simple models for
more detailed ones, adding engine sounds that may
actually change based on your tone speed and
adding effects like smoke and fire to make
the crashes look better.
And that's it for our video.